Is this... the island where the people outside living?
这就是…外面的人所住的岛么
Isn't it abandoned?
这不是一片废墟
Tell me the truth.
怎么回事
You don't mean this is your world right?
你敢说这就是你们的世界？
Oni, stop it!
欧尼 住手！
Oni!
欧尼！
Seems you guys actually don't know anything.
你们真的是 什么也不知道呢
We did not know anything.
我们什么都不知道
Nothing other than the mud whale... Nothing.
对泥鲸以外的世界 一无所知
Translator
翻
ssnake
译
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
ssnake
Silence and melody, and the transient lives of Shirushi
静寂よ　旋律よ　儚き印よ
Timing
时 间 轴
zwc1991
zwc1991
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
砂上にこの地に　生き続けたのなら
If you have been living on the land, on the sea of sand
如果是在这沙海之上  生活下去
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
罪を纏う世界から　鯨の歌を聴いた…
In a sinned world, we have heard the whale's lied
在罪业重重的世界里  我们曾侧耳倾听鲸鱼的歌唱…
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
運命を　感情を　抱くべき子たちよ
Our fate and our emotions, my beloved children
不论命运  还是感情  亲爱的孩子们哟
さ き
さ  き
その先へ　その未来へ
その先へ　その未来へ
Towards the future, go ahead
向着未来  向着前方
導かれたのなら
導かれたのなら
If you can be our guide
只要有你指引前路
幾千の声　空想の地へ
幾千の声　空想の地へ
Thousands of words, leaving for the fantasy lands
万千寄语  向着空想的彼岸
舵を切って行こうとした
舵を切って行こうとした
Steering towards the opposite
相信信念调转方向
バラード
バラード
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
幾千の声　砂の海の譚歌
Thousands of songs, they are the ballads of the sea of sand
万千欢声  是沙海的歌谣
F
雪 飘 工 作 室
L
雪 飘 工 作 室
What's this?
这是怎么回事
Graves.
墓
So many friends and fellows died...
这么多的朋友和伙伴都…
They are all buried by yourself?
这些…是你一个人埋葬的吗
How can you be this calm,
就这么漠然地一个人埋的么
you witch.
你是魔女啊
Why... Why did so many people have to die?
为什么…这么多人都不得不葬身此地
I pray, for the people who I don't know.
为素昧平生的你们祈祷
Hey, where are you heading?
喂 这是要去哪
Here.
这里
Waa!
哇！
Hey, what's this?
喂 这是什么
Answer me.
快说
Lykos?
黎可斯？
λύκος
λύκος
Lykos is not my name.
「黎可斯」不是我的名字
νοῦς
νοῦς
It's the name of this creature called nous.
是这个叫做「魂形」的生物的名字
Creature?
生物？
Νοῦς
νοῦς
Nous, means the shape of soul,
魂形… 灵魂的形状
is a creature that absorbs emotions from human beings.
是以人的「感情」为食的生物
We have been...
我们把自己的感情
λύκος
λύκος
feeding Lykos with our feelings as its nutrition.
交给这个「黎可斯」作为它的养分
That's why we have flat minds.
所以我们的心灵平淡如水
νοῦς
νοῦς
People who discovered the nous decided to deposit their emotions with them.
发现魂形的人类 把自己的感情交给了它们
Cuz emotions will destroy the world.
因为感情会让世界毁灭
It's not what we need.
是不需要的东西
In the world outside, where you want to know,
在你们所渴望了解的外面的世界
απάθεια
απάθεια
people without emotions command the apatheia with no heart
没有感情的人们操纵着没有心灵的傀儡士兵
to fight in an endless war.
进行着无尽的战争
It's such a world.
这样的世界
Is there particularly anything you want from our world?
你们所希冀的东西 难道会在我们的世界里？
Go back, and leave me here.
留下我回去吧
I will die on this ship by myself.
我要只身一人 死在这座船上
Lykos...
黎可斯…
I don't even mind.
我倒是无所谓
I don't care if there's a war or not.
管他战争什么的
I just want to escape from the mud whale.
我就不想一辈子被关在泥鲸上
If I can get out there,
要是能从那里解脱…
I'm willing to give all my feelings to you!
我的感情什么的要多少给多少
Stop, Oni! It's dangerous!
欧尼！ 不行 危险…
Ah!
啊！
What...
这是什么…
There are hundreds, thousands...
有成百… 上千的…
no, numbers of minds passing by and disappearing.
不计其数的人的「心灵」从我脑海里穿流而过 随之消逝
Oh my, I know this chaos...
对了 这是… 这个混沌是
hypergraphia
hypergraphia
When I can't stop writing,
当我无法停止书写时
I see this picture.
脑海中浮现的情景
Benihi?
贝妮希…
No, this is my memory.
不行 这是我的记忆
No way!
不行
I'm sad for it, but I don't want to get rid of it!
就算是悲伤的感情 我也不想忘却
Lykos.
黎可斯
Hey guys!
喂
You certainly know what you did right?
你们知道自己做了些什么吗
Chakuro!
查克罗
Are you OK?
没事吧
Chakuro? Hey Chakuro!
查克罗？ 查克罗！
Ah... Sami?
啊… 莎米？
You saw a lot of gravestones.
你们看到了许许多多的墓碑…
Are they really the only things you have seen?
真的仅此而已吗？
Yep.
是的
Chakuro, what about you?
查克罗呢？
Yes, nothing else.
是的 别的什么都没…
Let's believe what you two said.
知道了 就相信你们说的吧
Taisha, tell everyone,
台霞 告诉大家
traveling to that island is strictly prohibited.
今后一律禁止前往那座岛屿
So the procurement of goods is...
那么 物资的搜集就…
Canceled, you can't even take a needle.
一针一线都不许拿
Cool your head a bit here.
待这冷静冷静
So Oni, you were OK?
欧尼你没事吗？
Your heart wasn't taken by that right?
那时候 没有被吸走心灵吧
I saw strange stuffs at that time.
我啊 那时候看到了奇怪的东西
I believe, it's an creature that can truly absorb your heart.
那个…真的是会夺取心灵的生物呢
For just a moment...
只有一刹那
I saw it for a split second.
只看到了一刹那
The war of the outside world
外面的世界的战争
sentikinesis
thymia
is a war using thymia, I think.
是情念力的战争吧
That girl must be able of it, right?
那个女的也会用的吧
Oni, I'd leave it far away.
欧尼 不行的
Haven't you thing the graves?
你也见到了那些坟墓吧
I start to be scared about the world outside.
我啊 开始觉得外面的世界有点可怕了
Wait, why didn't you help me at that time!
说回来 你那时候怎么不拉我一把
If Lycos didn't give me a...
要不是黎可斯救了我…
Strange.
咦？
That's why we have flat minds.
所以我们的心灵平淡如水
Then why did she help me?
可是这样的话 为什么要救我呢
Chakuro.
查克罗
Masoo.
玛索
I'm finishing my meal...
我这就吃…
Nope, you're released.
不是 是释放
Huh?
诶？
Only you.
只有你啊
There's a guy who saw you were forced to go with Oni.
有人看到了你是被欧尼强行拖过去的
I wasn't really forced to go, though...
虽然并不完全是被强迫的…
You are lucky, you get released at a good timing.
你运气不错啊 赶在这个节骨眼上被放出来
What?
嗯？
Chakuro!
查克罗
Around the mud whale,
有一种被称为「星蝗」的大型蝗虫栖息在泥鲸周围
They live on eating wastes from the mud whale.
他们以泥鲸的废弃物为食谋生
They metamorphose into a structure suitable for long range movement
当它们的种群密度升高后 就会变成适合长期移动的形态
They start emitting lights and moving far away at midnight.
在深夜发出光亮 开始大迁徙
We call it a locust phenomenon.
我们将之称为「飞蝗现象」
Hurry up!
抓紧了
We need to take a good place before it gets dark!
天黑之前得抢到好地方
Yep yep.
是是
Sami, Nezu, Lo,
莎米 涅兹 洛
wait a moment please!
不好意思 请稍微等我一下
Hey, Chakuro!
喂 查克罗
Where are you going?
你去哪里啊
May I help you?
请问您怎么了？
Are you still suffering from the injury?
您的伤口还痛吗？
My name is Neli, I am taking care of the presbyters at this tower.
我是这座塔上负责照顾长老们生活的奈莉
I am just a Muin, but please don't hesitate to ask me if you need any assistance.
虽然我只是「无印」 但如果有什么要求请不要客气
Tell the presbyters!
请告诉长老们
I need that ship!
我离不开那座船
λύκος
λύκος
Get me back to Lykos!
让我回到「黎可斯」身边
I can't leave it.
我不能离开它
If I have feelings...
当我有了感情…
I'll be mad.
会让我不胜其苦
I have to take my minds away.
不把心灵抹杀掉的话…
It is normal to have minds.
人有心灵才是普通的
You will soon get used to it.
你很快就会适应的
Here you are!
找到了
Chakuro!
查克罗？
Neli, please!
奈莉 拜托
Let me take Lykos out!
能让我把黎可斯带出去吗
Take her out...
带出去…
You want to get sent to the internal again?
你还想被关到体内去吗
I want to see the locust with her
我想跟她一起看飞蝗
as well as my friends.
想让黎可斯… 和我的朋友一起
That's a deal, thank you.
那拜托了
Neli you should take a good place as soon as possible, too.
奈莉也早点去找个好地方啊
Leave me.
放开我
No,
不行
I can't leave you alone even if you don't have minds.
哪怕你没有心灵 我也放不下你
You made so many graves for your fellows, all by yourself.
你孤身一人 为那么多的伙伴修了坟墓
I can never leave such a good girl alone.
这样的女孩子 我怎么能置之不理
What? With Lykos?
咦 让黎可斯也来？
The girl from that island? Great!
那个岛上的姑娘？ 不是吧
Eh... Hi, call me Nezu.
你…你好 我叫涅兹
So, what should we do?
然后 你打算怎么办
If she is found, then it's much more than not being able to see the locust.
要是被谁发现了 就不止是看不了飞蝗这么简单了
No problem!
没事
By taking my anti sand cloak this way,
把我的防沙斗篷给她套上
she will never be recognized.
就认不出是谁了
How you dare renting your dirty cloak to a girl
我说你啊 洗都不洗的斗篷就这么给女孩子穿
No, give it back to me!
啊 还是还给我
But then how can I hide you!
啊 可是这样就露馅了
There are spaces on the top of the 4th tower.
第4塔的顶上还空着
Let's go there.
咱们去那吧
Ahh, I can't move anymore.
啊 我不行了
I'm tired!
累了
Only a few more steps to go.
马上就到顶上了
But...
可是…
You can do it.
加油
Chakuro,
查克罗
lift me up.
抱我
Wh... What?
啊 什么？
What are you talking about?
你…你说什么呢
You lifted my up last time!
上次不就抱我上去了吗
Last time...
上次…
The previous locust phenomenon is three years ago, right?
上次飞蝗是三年前的事了吧
Lift me up! I can't walk anymore!
抱我 走不动了！
Yeah.
嗯
It's impossible now!
抱不动了啦
You are getting heavy!
莎米都这么重了！
Sami is not heavy at all!
莎米才不重呢！
Chakuro's spiteful!
查克罗就知道欺负人！
Idiot! Stingy!
白痴！ 小气鬼！
See, you can walk yourself
瞧 这不是还走得动吗
Sami, are you OK?
莎米 没事吧
Shall I carry you on my back?
要我背你吗
No, thanks!
不用
Mom,
妈妈
we're yet to see Mr. Grassho?
小虫虫 还没到吗
Soon you will.
马上就到了
Only a few steps left, keep at it!
再加加油吧
Hey!
好嘞
Let's go for it!
这样就快了
Masoo, thank you.
玛索 不好意思
You're welcome.
没关系的
I have lost my child in an accident by the sea of sand.
自从我家小子在沙海事故里走了以后
Since then I love every small child.
我就一直放不下小孩子
Excuse me, Kuchiba.
那个 库奇巴
It's painful.
好痛的
What?
诶？
You hold my hand too hard.
手 捏得太紧了
Ah! So..Sorry!
啊 不…不好意思
Still yet?
还没来吗
What's up?
怎么了？
Have you seen?
…你看到了吗？
Grassho? Where?
蝗虫？ 在哪？
I entered the military academy when I was 7.
我七岁的时候被送去军队的培训学校
I headed to the dormitory with my family.
我和家人一起去的学校宿舍
And that was the day I parted from my family.
那天我就和他们永别了
But for us, whose emotions have been taken away, we didn't even have a feeling.
但对于没有感情的我们来说 并没有留下什么感慨
The way to the dorm was long and steep, and my luggage was heavy.
通往宿舍的道路又长又陡 行李还很重
Stand up!
站起来
How can you be a good soldier with that!
像这样怎么当个优秀的军人
I saw it!
看到了！
Yes, I saw it.
我看到了
I saw your memory inside that creature.
在那个生物里 看到了那个时候的你
I was not even troubling with it.
我一直… 觉得那是无所谓的事情
Why it becomes so painful to me?
为什么 如今会如此伤感…
Lykos,
黎可斯
you do have your heart in you.
因为你 确实有着心灵啊
The same!
一样的
We are the same.
你和我们是一样的
Hey, maybe the mud whale
呐 说不定有一天
will get to where your family live some day.
泥鲸会漂游到你家人附近
Also you will never be a soldier here.
而且在泥鲸这儿
You will never die in a fight here in the mud whale.
征召入伍 战死沙场这种事情是不会发生的
Lykos, let's stay here.
黎可斯 在这里生活吧
Chakuro.
查克罗
What?
怎么了？
I have something important to say to you.
我…有件事情必须要告诉你们
This ship...
这座船…
Hey!
喂
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina.
「法莱那」…
I wonder where are they going to.
这些虫子…是要去哪里呢
We wanna go somewhere far away!
我们也好想去个遥远的世界啊！
July 8, 93 S.S.
砂刑历93年7月8日
We recognized a locust phenomenon.
确认飞蝗现象
The crowd was flying above the mud whale with lights emitted.
虫群在泥鲸上空不断飞舞发光
And they leaved for somewhere far away in the sea of sand by the dawn.
而到黎明时分则启程向着沙海远方飞去
Chakuro!
查克罗！
Get up now, take your breakfast!
快给我起来 吃饭
Oh shit, you dumb-ass!
啊够了 你这家伙！
I've had enough!
给我像话点！
I can't stand teaming with you any longer!
我早就受够跟你一班了
Troubling me all the time, you destroyer!
destroyer
Tobi, listen.
我说啊 托比
Since our parents died,
自从我们父母去世
we started to live together.
我们开始共同生活以后
I have been looking after your younger brother and sister, haven't I?
我可没少帮你照看弟弟妹妹哦
We are helping each other, right?
这不是彼此彼此么
Chakuro, you're sprinkling.
查克罗 漏嘴巴
You have been looked after, haven't you!
这是谁照看谁啊
How dare you call it helping each other!
还有脸说彼此彼此！
I'm heading the farm!
我今天要去种田
It's my duty today!
我先走了
Suo.
苏澳
Bro~
哥哥
Wah, my bro's full of mud.
哇 哥哥一身泥
I can't work as fast as you.
我比大家干活慢
So I started earlier.
所以先来干活了
Where?
咦？
My bro is good at everything except for physical fitness.
哥哥什么都好 就是运动神经不行
Let's sow together.
我们去播种吧
The locust yesterday is really beautiful.
昨天的飞蝗 好漂亮呢
Yeah.
嗯
How about Lykos after that?
那之后 黎可斯怎么样了？
I sent her back to the central tower.
送她回中央塔了
Since I brought her out secretly.
毕竟是悄悄带出来的嘛
I see.
这样啊
Sami, Chakuro,
莎米 查克罗
do me a favor please.
接下来拜托了
I have works to do at the presbytery.
我要去帮长老会做事
OK!
好的
So.. sorry.
抱 抱歉
Fine.
没事
Neli?
奈莉？
Suo.
苏澳
What's wrong?
怎么了？
That is...
那个…
Lykos said she has something to tell the presbyters.
黎可斯说有话要传达给各位长老
She seems very serious.
看起来很是焦虑
However, the presbytery refused to meet her.
可是 长老会却拒绝跟她见面…
And in fact...
据说…
The presbytery has sent the vigilante group out behind Taisha-sama.
长老会瞒着台霞阿姨
It seems that they are alerting the surrounding sea areas.
派警备团出海加强了周边的警备
Let me see her.
我去见她吧
You can't.
不行的
She is guarded and nobody is allowed to meet her.
有人把门 说是谁都不让见她的
What do you want?
请问有何贵干？
You can't enter.
不能进去的
I have the permission.
我得到了许可
Er, I've never heard it...
我 我怎么不知…
You heard it just now.
你现在知道了
Right?
对吧
Excuse me, I...
打扰了 我是…
Please! Let me talk to the representative of this island!
求求你 带我去见这座岛的代表
I have something important that I must tell you!
我有很重要的…必须要告诉你们的事情
Tell me please.
那告诉我吧
Taisha-sama.
台霞姐姐
I accidentally threw away Chakuro's records.
查克罗的记录飞跑了
I have to pick them up.
得去捡回来
I will let others do it for you.
我派人去
That boy said he want to know the world,
那孩子说想了解世界
so he keeps the records.
所以要留下记录
I have the same feeling now.
如今 我也怀着同样的心情
However...
可是…
The presbytery is hiding the girl of the adrift island from us.
长老会把漂流岛上的少女藏起来不让我们相见
We have no choice.
没有办法
The presbytery is conventionally controlling over the mud whale.
泥鲸的领导权 依惯例是掌握在长老会手中的
Yeah, I do understand.
嗯 我知道的
Every "Muin" can become the presbyter when over 61 years old.
年满61岁的全体无印 都会成为长老会的成员
Then they'll be informed with the history of mud whale
并能得知泥鲸的历史以及它与世界的关系
Chief doesn't have any political power.
首长并没有政治实权
I'm only required to be a symbol being loved by the public.
只是为了塑造一个受民众爱戴的对象
There are 19 years before I can enter the presbytery.
我还有19年才能进入长老会
Before that, I'm just a puppet.
在那之前 我都像木偶一般
I have to keep playing as a well-made idol.
不得不饰演受人崇拜的偶像
It... It isn't that bad!
有…有什么不好的！
I don't care Taisha-sama is a puppet or not.
不管台霞姐姐是木偶还是什么
I always support you!
我都永远支持你！
If it's for the sake of mud whale,
只要是为了泥鲸
I will try to be a good puppet.
让我成为一个好的木偶吧
What's that?
怎么回事
σκύλος
σκύλος
Skulax here, starting the operation now.
斯奇洛斯 展开作战行动
Escape from here, as soon as possible!
快从这里逃走 越快越好！
This island...
这座岛…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Fallaina...
「法莱那」…
Chakuro, is that a sand dolphin?
查克罗 那是沙海豚么
You,
你们这些…
φάλαινα
φάλαινα
The sinners of the whale, are targeted.
「鲸的罪人」 将会被攻击
Sinners?
罪人？
We are?
我们是罪人？
My records as the official record clerk
我作为工作留下的正式记录
ended this day.
到今天为止了
The record about the mud whale, in the future,
今后关于泥鲸的记录
will be my personal
是我个人的…
The second section
第 二 节
The Sinners of the Whale
第 二 节
Fallaina
鲸 的 罪 人 们
diary.
日记
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
Staring into the trace of the dried sea
眺望昔日的大海
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
I will draw the other side I have never seen
描绘未知的彼岸
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
If you remain your heart in captivity
如果囚禁起心灵  一如过往
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
You may live without knowing the pain
又怎会经历如此悲伤
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
The one who told the beautiful story
是谁讲述起美好的希望
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
Can not wait for the dawn
让我等不及黎明
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
Until beyond the end of world, I am swimming
向着天涯海角扬帆起航
虫の唄
虫の唄
Listen to the insects' song
彻夜虫鸣
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
That night is our memory
回忆里与你一起侧耳倾听
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
Just link hand in hand
只是双手相牵
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
No matter it is twilight or a distant country
不论夕阳  还是远方
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
Born in a short chapter
在这短暂苍渺的一章里
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう
But let us go and embrace that dream
一起追逐梦想
The third section
第 三 节
I Care No More about That World
这 样 的 世 界